<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be inqvired of. 1548</title>
            <title>Visitation Articles. 1548.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1553-1556 : Cranmer)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00155</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10148</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121382</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856565</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22137</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00155)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 11:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be inqvired of. 1548</title>
                  <title>Visitation Articles. 1548.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Province of Canterbury. Archbishop (1553-1556 : Cranmer)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>the laste daie of August, M.D,xlviii: in the second yere of the reigne of our most drad &amp; souereigne lorde Kyng Edvvarde the, VI: by Richard Grafton printer to his highnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted in London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The drop-head title on A2r reads: "Articles to be enquired of, in visitacions to bee had, within the Diocesse of Cantorbury: in the seconde yere of the reigne of our moste drad souereigne Lorde Edward the. VI. by the grace of God, Kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande; defender of the faithe and in yearth of the Churche of Englande and also of Irelande, the supreme hedde.".</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>In this issue, A2r last line has: Kynge.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Sion College Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Canterbury.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶Articles to be enquired of, in viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions to bee had, within the Dioceſſe of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torbury: in the ſeconde yere of the reigne of our moſte drad ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne Lorde Edward the <hi>.VI.</hi> by the grace of God, Kyng of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defender of the faithe and in yearth of the Churche of Englande and alſo of Irelande, the ſupreme hedde.</head>
            <p n="1"> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, whether Perſones, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, and Curates, and euery of them haue purely and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, without colour or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, foure times in the yere at the leaſt, preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the vſurped power, pretenſed aucthoritie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiccion of the biſhop of Rome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether thei haue preached and declared likewiſe iiii times of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere at the leaſt, that the kynges maieſties power, aucthoritie, and prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence, within his Realmes and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, is the higheſt power vnder God.</p>
            <p n="3"> Item, whether any perſone hath by writyng, Cyphryng, preachyng, or teachyng, deede or act obſtinatly holden, and ſtande with to extoll, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furthe, maintein or defend the aucthoritie, iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or power of the biſhop of Rome, or of his ſea heretofore claimed and vſurped, or by any pretenſe, obſtinatly or maliciouſly, inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted any thyng for the extollyng of the ſame, or any parte thereof.</p>
            <p n="4"> Item, whether in their common praiers, thei vſe not the Collettes made for the Kynge, and
<pb facs="tcp:22137:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
make not ſpeciall mencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his maieſties name in theſame.</p>
            <p n="5">Item, whether thei do not euery ſonday and holy day, with the collectes of the Engliſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, ſaie the praier ſet furthe by the Kynges maieſtie for peace betwene England &amp; Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</p>
            <p n="6">Item, whether thei haue not remoued, taken awaie, &amp; vtterly extincted and deſtroied, in their Churches, Chapelles, and houſes, all Images, all ſhrines, couerynges of ſhrines, all Tables, candelſtickes, trindels, or rolles of waxe, pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Paintynges, and all other monumentes of fained miracles, Pilgrimages, Idolatrie and Superſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that there remain no memorie of theſame, in walles, glaſewindowes, or els wher.</p>
            <p n="7">Item, whether thei haue exhorted moued and ſtirred their pariſhoners, to do the like in euery of their houſes.</p>
            <p n="8">Item, whether thei haue declared to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhoners, the articles concernyng the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of certain ſuperfluous holy daies, and doen their indeuor to perſwade the ſaied pariſhoners to kepe and obſerue theſame articles inuiolably and whether any of thoſe abrogate daies, hath been kepte as holy daies, and by whoſe occaſion thei were ſo kept.</p>
            <p n="9">Item, whether thei haue diligently, duely, and reuerently, miniſtred the Sacramentes in their Cures.</p>
            <p n="10">Item, whether thei haue preached, or cauſed to bee preached, purely and ſincerely the woorde
<pb facs="tcp:22137:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of god, in euery of their Cures, euery quarter of the yere, once at the leaſt, exhorting their pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoners, to the workes commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and not to workes deuiſed by mennes pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies beſides ſcripture, as wearyng or praiyng vpon beades, or ſuche like.</p>
            <p n="11"> Item whether thei ſuffre any torches, candel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Tapers, or any other lightes to bee in your Churches, but onely two lightes vpon the high Aultare.</p>
            <p n="12"> Item, whether thei haue not euery holy day when thei haue no ſermon, immediatly after the Goſpell, ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, plainly, and diſtinctly, recited to their pariſhoners in the pulpit, the <hi>Paternoſter</hi> the <hi>crede,</hi> and the .x. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes in Engliſhe.</p>
            <p n="13"> Item, whether euery Lent, thei examine ſuche perſones as commeth to Confeſſion to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thei canne recite the <hi>Pater noster</hi> the Articles of our faith, &amp; the .x. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in Engliſh.</p>
            <p n="14"> Item, whether thei haue charged fathers and mothers, maſters and gouernours of youthe to bryng them vp in ſome verteous ſtudy or occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacion.</p>
            <p n="15"> Item, whether ſuche beneficed menne, as bee lawfully abſent from their benefices, doe leaue their Cure to a rude and vnlearned perſon, and not to an honeſt well learned and expert Curate whiche can and will teach you holſom doctrine.</p>
            <p n="16"> Item, whether in euery Cure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, thei haue prouided one boke of the whole Bible of the largeſt volume in Engliſhe, and the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſis
<pb facs="tcp:22137:3"/>
of Eraſmus alſo in Engliſhe vpon the Goſpelles, and ſet vp theſame in ſome conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place in the Church, where their pariſhoners maie moſte commodiouſly reſorte to theſame.</p>
            <p n="17">Item, whether thei haue diſcoraged any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> readyng of any part of the Bible, either in Latin or in Engliſhe, but rather comforted and exhorted euery perſone to reade the ſame, as the very liuely woorde of God, and the ſpeciall foode of mannes ſoule</p>
            <p n="18">Item, whether Perſones, Vicars, Curates, and other prieſtes, be common haunters and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorters to Tauernes, or Alehouſes, geuyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfes to drinkyng, riotyng, or plaiyng at vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull games, and doo not occupie theim ſelfes in the reading or hearyng, of ſome parte of holy ſcripture, or in ſome other Godly exerciſe.</p>
            <p n="19">Item, whether thei haue admitted any man to preache in their cures, not beyng lawfully licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thereunto, or haue refuſed or denied ſuche to preache, as haue been licenſed accordyngly.</p>
            <p n="20">Item, whether thei which haue heretofore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to their pariſhoners, any thing to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling or ſetting furth of pilgrimages reliques or Images, or lightyng of ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dells, kiſſing, kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, deckyng of theſame Images, or any ſuche ſuperſticion, haue not openly recanted and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued theſame.</p>
            <p n="21">Item, whether thei haue one boke or regiſter ſafely kepte, wherein thei write the daie of euery Weddyng, Chriſtenyng, and Buriyng,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="22"> Item, whether thei haue exhorted the people to obedience, to the kynges maieſtie and his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and Charitie and loue, one to a nother.</p>
            <p n="23"> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether thei haue admoniſhed their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhoners, that thei ought not to preſume, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament, of the body and bloud of Chriſte, before thei can perfectly the <hi>pater noſter</hi> the Articles of the faith, and the tenne commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in Engliſhe.</p>
            <p n="24"> Item, whether thei haue declared, and to their wittes and power haue perſwaded the people, that the maner and kind of faſting in Lent, and other daies in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yere, is but a mere poſitiue law, and that therfore al perſones, hauyng iuſt cauſe of ſicknes, or other neceſſitie, or beyng licenſed by the kynges maieſtie, maie moderatly eate all kynde of meates, without grudge or ſcruple of conſcience.</p>
            <p n="25"> Item, whether thei be reſident vpon their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, and kepe hoſpitalitie or no, and if thei be abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or kepe no hoſpitalitie, whether thei do make due diſtribucions emong the poore pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoners or not.</p>
            <p n="26"> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether Perſones, Vicars, Clarkes, and other beneficed men, hauyng yerely to diſpende an hundred pounde, doo not finde competently one ſcholer in the Vniuerſitie, of Cambridge or Oxforde or ſome Grammer ſchole, and for as many hundred poundes, as euery of them maie diſpende, ſo many ſcholes likewiſe to be founde by them, &amp; what be their names, that thei ſo find</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:4"/>
            <p n="27"> Item, whether Proprietaries, Perſones, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, and Clarkes, hauyng Churches, Chapel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les or Manſions, dooe kepe their Chauncelles. Rectories, Vicareges, and all other houſes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteignyng to them, in due reperacions.</p>
            <p n="28">Item whether thei haue counſailed, or moued their pariſhoners, rather to praie in a to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue not knowen, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Engliſhe, or to put their truſt in any preſcribed nombre of praiers, as in ſaiyng ouer a nomber of beades or other like.</p>
            <p n="29">Item, whether thei haue red the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Iniunctions, euery quarter of the yere, the firſt holy day of the ſame quarter.</p>
            <p n="30">Item, whether the Perſons, Vicars Curates and other prieſtes, beeyng vnder the degree of a bacheler of diuinitie, haue of their awne the new Teſtament, both in Latin and in Engliſhe and the paraphraſe of Eraſmus vpon theſame.</p>
            <p n="31">Item, whether within euery Churche, he that miniſtereth haue red or cauſe to be red, the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle or Goſpell in Engliſhe, and not in Latin, either in the Pulpit or ſome other mete place, ſo as the people maie here theſame.</p>
            <p n="32">Item, whether euery Sondaie and holy daie at Matyns, thei haue read or cauſe to bee read, plainly and diſtinctly in the ſaid place, one Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter of the newe Teſtament in Engiſhe, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the Leſſons, and at Euenſong after Magnificat, one Chapiter of the old teſtament.</p>
            <p n="33">Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether thei haue not at Matins omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted three leſſons, when, ix. ſhould haue been read
<pb facs="tcp:22137:4"/>
in the Churche, and at Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſong the Reſpondes with all the Memories.</p>
            <p n="34"> Item, whether thei haue declared to their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, that ſainct Markes daie, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens of the abrogate holy daies ſhould not bee faſted.</p>
            <p n="35"> Item, whether thei haue the Proceſſion boke in Engliſhe, and haue ſaied or ſong the ſaid Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany in any other place, but vpon their knees in the middeſt of their Churche, and whether thei vſe any other proceſſion, or omit the ſaid Letany at any tyme, or ſaie it or ſyng it in ſuche ſorte as the people connot vnderſtande theſame.</p>
            <p n="36"> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether thei haue put out of their chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che bokes, this worde <hi>Papa</hi> and the name and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Thomas Bequet, and praiers hauyng rubrices, conteinyng pardones or indulgences, and al other ſuperſticious lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and praiers.</p>
            <p n="37"> Item, whether thei bid not the beades accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the order, appoynted by the Kynges Maieſtie.</p>
            <p n="38"> Item, whether thei haue opened and declared vnto you, the true vſe of Ceremonies, (that is to ſaie) that thei be no workers nor workes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacion, but onely outwarde ſignes and tokens, to put vs in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thynges of higher perfeccion.</p>
            <p n="39"> Item, whether thei haue taught and declared to their pariſhoners, that thei maie with a ſafe &amp; quiet confidence in the tyme of Harueſt, labour vpon the holy and feſtiuall daies, and if ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticiouſly
<pb facs="tcp:22137:5"/>
thei abſtein from working vpon thoſe daies, that then thei doo greuouſly offende and diſpleaſe God.</p>
            <p n="40">Item, whether thei haue admitted any perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the Communion, beeyng openly knowen to be out of charitie with their neighbors.</p>
            <p n="41">Item, whether the Deanes, Archedeacons, Maſters of Hoſpitalles, and Prebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>daries haue peached by theimſelfes perſonally, twiſe euery yere at the leaſt.</p>
            <p n="42">Item, whether thei haue prouided, and haue a ſtrong Cheſte for the poore mennes Boxe, and ſet and faſtened theſame, nere to the high aultar.</p>
            <p n="43">Item, whether thei haue diligently called v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, exhorted and moued their pariſhoners, and ſpecially when thei make their Teſtamentes, to geue to the ſaied poore mennes Boxe, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore Cheſt, whiche thei wer wont to beſtowe vpon Pardonnes, Pilgrema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Trentalles, Maſſes ſatiſfactorie, deckyng of Images, offeryng of Candelles, geuyng to Friers, and vpon other like blinde deuocions.</p>
            <p n="44">Item, whether thei haue denied to Viſite the ſicke, or Burie the dedde, beeyng brought to the Churche.</p>
            <p n="45">Item, whether thei haue bought their benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or come to them by fraude or deceipt.</p>
            <p n="46">Item, whether thei haue euery Sondaie, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people be moſte gathered, red one of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melies, in ordre as thei ſtande in the boke, ſette furthe by the kynges maieſtie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="47"> Item, whether thei do not omit prime and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, when thei haue any ſermon or Homelie.</p>
            <p n="48"> Item, whether thei haue ſaied or ſong any Maſſe, in any Oratory, Chapell, or any mannes houſe, not beyng hallowed.</p>
            <p n="49"> Item, whether thei haue geuen open monicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their Pariſhoners, that thei ſhould not weare beades, nor praie vpon them.</p>
            <p n="50"> Item, whether thei haue moued their Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoners, liyng vpon their death beddes, or at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other tyme, to beſtowe any parte of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, vpon Trentalles, Maſſes Satiſfactory or any ſuche blynd deuocions.</p>
            <p n="51"> Item, whether thei take any Trentalles, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Maſſes Satiſfactory to ſay or ſyng, for the quicke or the dedde.</p>
            <p n="52"> Item, whether thei haue geuen open monicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their pariſhoners, to detect and preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to their Ordenarie, all adulterers and fornicators, and ſuche men as haue two wiues liuyng, and ſuche women as haue twoo huſbandes liuyng, within their pariſhes.</p>
            <p n="53"> Item, whether thei haue not moniſhed their Pariſhoners openly, that thei ſhould not ſell, geue, nor otherwiſe alienate, any of their Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che goodes.</p>
            <p n="54"> Item, whether thei or any of theim, dooe kepe mo benefices, and other Eccleſiaſticall promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, then thei ought to do, not hauyng ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent licence, and diſpenſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therunto, and how many thei be, and their names.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:6"/>
            <p n="55"> Item, whether thei miniſter the Communion, any otherwiſe then only after ſuch fourme and maner, as is ſet furthe by the Kynges Maieſtie, in the boke of the Communion,</p>
            <p n="56">Item, whether thei halowed and deliuered to the people, any Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delles vpon Candelmas day any aſſhes vpon Aſhe Wedneſdai, or any Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vpon Palme Sondaie laſte paſt.</p>
            <p n="57">Item, whether thei had vpon Good Fridaie laſt paſt, the Sepulchres with their lightes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng the Sacrament therin.</p>
            <p n="58">Item, whether thei vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eaſter euen laſt paſt, halowed the Font, Fire, or Paſchall, or had any Paſchall ſet vp or burnyng in their Churches,</p>
            <p n="59">Item, whether youre Perſones and Vicars, haue admitted any curates to ſerue their Cures whiche were not firſt examined and allowed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by my lord of Cantorbury, Maſter Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, or their officers.</p>
            <p n="60">Item, whether you knowe any perſone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in youre pariſhe, or els where, that is a letter of the worde of God, to be red in Engliſhe, or ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely preached, or of the execucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the kynges Maieſties Iniunccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or other his Maieſties procedynges, in matters of religion.</p>
            <p n="61">Item, whether euery pariſhe haue prouided a cheſt with twoo lockes and keyes, for the boke of Weddyng, Chriſtenyng, and buriyng.</p>
            <p n="62">Item, whether in the tyme of the Letany, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other common praier, in the tyme of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or Homely, and when the prieſt readeth the
<pb facs="tcp:22137:6"/>
ſcripture to the pariſhoners, any perſone haue departed out of the churche, without a iuſte and neceſſary cauſe.</p>
            <p n="63"> Item, whether any belles haue bee knolled or rong at the tyme of the premiſſes.</p>
            <p n="64"> Item, whether any perſone hath abuſed the Ceremonies, as in caſtyng holi Water vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bed, or bearyng aboute hym, holy Bread, ſainct Ihons Goſpell, ringyng of holy Belles, or ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of priuate holy daies, as Taylors, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, Brewers, Smithes, Shoomakers, and ſuche other.</p>
            <p n="65"> Item, whether the money co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng and riſyng of any cattell, or other moueable ſtockes of the Churche, and money geuen or bequethed, to the findyng of Torches, lightes, tapers, or lampes, (not paied out of ony landes) haue not been em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to the poore mennes Cheſt.</p>
            <p n="66"> Item, who hath the ſaied ſtockes, and money in their handes, and what be their names.</p>
            <p n="67"> Item, whether any vndiſcrete perſons do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitably contempne, and abuſe prieſtes and miniſters of the churche.</p>
            <p n="68"> Item, whether thei that vnderſtande not the Latin, doo praie vpon any primer, but the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhe Primer, ſet furthe by the kynges Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties aucthoritie, and whether thei that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Latin, doo vſe any other then the Latin Primer, ſet furthe by like aucthoritie.</p>
            <p n="69"> Item, whether there bee any other Grammer taught in any ſchole within this Dioceſſe, then
<pb facs="tcp:22137:7"/>
that whiche is ſet furth by the kynges maieſtie.</p>
            <p n="70"> Item, whether any perſone kepe their churche holy daie, and the dedicacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daie, any otherwiſe or at any other tyme, then is appoynted by the kynges maieſtie.</p>
            <p n="71">Item, whether the ſeruice in the Churche, bee doen at due and conuenient howers.</p>
            <p n="72">Item, whether any haue vſed to common, ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and talke in the Churche, in the tyme of the common praier, Readyng of the Homelie, Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng, Readyng or declaryng of the ſcripture.</p>
            <p n="73">Item, whether any haue wilfully mainteined and defended, any Hereſies, Errors, or falſe opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, contrary to the faithe of Chriſte, and holy ſcripture.</p>
            <p n="74">Item, whether any bee common dronkerdes, ſwearers, or blaſphemers of the name of God.</p>
            <p n="75">Item, whether any haue committed adultery, fornicacion or inceſt, or be common baudes, and receiuers of ſuche euill perſones, or vehemently ſuſpected of any of the premiſſes.</p>
            <p n="76">Item, whether any bee braulers, ſlaunderers, chiders, ſkolders, &amp; ſowers of diſcorde, betwene one perſone and another.</p>
            <p n="77">Item, whether you knowe any that vſe char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, Sorcerie, Enchauntmentes, Witchecraft, Sotheſaiyng, or any like crafte inuented by the Deuill.</p>
            <p n="78">Item, whether the Churches, Pulpittes, and other neceſſaries apparteignyng to theſame, be ſufficiently repared.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:7"/>
            <p n="79"> Item, whether you knowe any, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of their awne pariſhe Churche, doo reſort to any other Churche.</p>
            <p n="80"> Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether any Inholders, or Alehouſeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, do vſe commonly to ſell meate and drinke, in the tyme of the common Praier, Preachyng, Readyng of the Homelies, or ſcripture.</p>
            <p n="81"> Item, whether you knowe any to bee maried, within the degrees prohibited by the Lawes of God, or that be ſeperated or diuorſed, without a iuſt cauſe, alowed by the lawe of God, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſuche haue maried again.</p>
            <p n="82"> Item, whether you knowe any, to haue made priuie contractes of Matrimonie, not callyng twoo or mo thereunto.</p>
            <p n="83"> Item, whether thei haue maried ſolemnly, the bannes not firſt lawfully aſked.</p>
            <p n="84"> Item, whether you knowe any Executors, or Adminiſtrators of dedde mennes goodes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che do not duely beſtowe ſuche of the ſaied goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, as wer geuen and bequethed, or appoynted to be deſtributed emong the poore people, repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng of high waies, fyndyng of poore ſcholers, or mariyng of poore maydes, or ſuche other like charitable deedes.</p>
            <p n="85"> Item, whether any do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempne maried prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, and for that thei be maried, will not receiue the communion, or other Sacramentes at their handes.</p>
            <p n="86"> Item, whether you knowe any that kepe in their houſes vndefaced, any abuſed or feined I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages,</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:8"/>
            <p>IMPRINTED IN LONDON the laſte daie of Auguſt, M.D, xlviii: in the ſecond yere of the reigne of our moſte drad &amp; ſouereigne lorde Kyng Edvvarde the, VI: By Richard Grafton Printer to his highnes: 1548.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:22137:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
